Landon and Howd Family Papers
Litchfield Historical Society
Landon and Howd Family Papers
1795-1936
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Howd, Frank, 1849-1933; Landon, James, 1770-1833
0.50
The papers of the Landon and Howd families of Salisbury, Conn., including bonds, correspondence, deeds, estate records, and other items. Family members reflected in the papers include James Landon (1744-1813) and his son James (1770-1833), Henry E. Howd, (1799-1878; son-in-law of the younger James Landon), and Henry E. Howd's son Frank E. Howd (1849-1933).
1999-18-0
Scope and Contents
The papers of the Landon and Howd families of Salisbury, Conn., including bonds, correspondence, deeds, estate records, and other items. Family members reflected in the papers include James Landon (1744-1813) and his son James (1770-1833), Henry E. Howd, (1799-1878; son-in-law of the younger James Landon), and Henry E. Howd's son Frank E. Howd (1849-1933).
John Landon (1720-1810) was one of four brothers who moved to Litchfield, Conn., with their father, James, in the 1720s. John moved to Salisbury, where his descendants continued to live for more than 200 years. His grandson James (1770-1833) married Sarah Lines and they had eight children, including Allen, Cynthia, Susanna, Charlotte, John, and Harriet. Cynthia married Henry E. Howd, the son of Eliphalet Howd (1767?-1832?) and Loly Clark Howd.
Eliphalet Howd and his family members lived in Canaan, Conn. and the surrounding towns in the late 1700s and early 1800s. Nineteenth-century sources indicate that he and his sons Asahel, Judah, and Henry were among the original settlers of Litchfield, Ohio, in 1830. The same sources state that all of the Howds settled permanently. The papers contain two letters written by James Landon in 1830 and 1831 to his daughter Cynthia and son-in-law in Litchfield, Ohio. But rather than remaining in Ohio, Henry and his family returned to Salisbury, possibly in connection with his father-in-law's death in 1833, which some sources say was due to drowning. Henry and Cynthia's first daughter was apparently born in Salisbury in 1838, and the 1840 and subsequent censuses and the obituaries of Henry and Cynthia place the family in the Connecticut town.
Besides the correspondence of Landon mentioned above, the collection contains correspondence received by Henry Howd's son Frank from the 1860s into the first decades of the twentieth century. Deeds trace the acquisition of land by James Landon through the early 1800s, although it has not been determined which James Landon is the purchaser. The collection also contains materials related to estates and among other items.
Arrangement of Materials
The papers are arranged in one series by type and then chronologically. Papers created prior to 1840 have been processed.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Howd family; Landon family
Genre/Form of Material:
Bonds (legal records); Correspondence; Deeds; Estate inventories; Licenses; Receipts; Theater programs; Wills
Geographic Name:
Litchfield (Ohio); Salisbury (Conn.); Western Reserve (Ohio)
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society on 01/01/1999.
Other Information
This collection was processed with support from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR) and the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Papers
  - Agreements, 1813, 1843 (Folder 1)
    - Landon, James and Bradley, Liman for wood, 1815 Mar 3 (Folder 1)
    - Landon, Henry and Belden & Miner for wood, 1843 Jun 15 (Folder 1)
  - Bill of sale, 1813 (Folder 2)
  - Bonds, 1813-1884 (Folder 3)
    - Landon, James to Warner, Benjamin, 1813 Jan 2 (Folder 3)
    - Goodrich, David to Landon, James, 1816 Oct 1 (Folder 3)
    - Steele, George and Alexander, John to the Trustees of Amherst College, 1884 Sep 23 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1830-1831 (Folder 4)
    - Landon, James to Howd, Cynthia Landon, 1830 Oct 24 (Folder 4)
    - Landon, James and [?] to Howd, Harry and Cynthia, 1831 Nov 27 and Dec 6 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1892 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1920, undated (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Christmas cards, 1936 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, empty envelopes (Folder 8)
  - Deeds, 1795-1802 (Folder 9)
    - Burrall, Jonathan to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1795 Jun (Folder 9)
    - Bacon, William to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1799 Feb 19 (Folder 9)
    - Robb, James to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1800 Sep 24 (Folder 9)
    - Moore, William to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1802 Dec 6 (Folder 9)
  - Deeds, 1805-1817 (Folder 10)
    - Clark, Rufus and Butler, Gideon to Landon, James interest in land and a grist mill and items in Canaan, Conn., 1805 Mar 21 (Folder 10)
    - Landon, James to Burrall, Jeremiah land in Canaan, Conn., 1809 Mar 27 (Folder 10)
    - Newell, Esther to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1814 Jul 1 (Folder 10)
    - Deming, Joel and Deming, Sally to Landon, James land in Salisbury, 1817 Jun 30 (Folder 10)
  - Deeds, 1819-1822 (Folder 11)
    - Landon, John to Landon, James land in Canaan, Conn., 1819 Mar 6 (Folder 11)
    - Landon, James to Howd, Eliphalet; Howd, Judah; and Howd, Henry land in Salisbury, Conn. [not completed], 181[?] (Folder 11)
    - Newell, Esther to Landon, James interest in a barn in Salisbury, 1820 Jul 22 (Folder 11)
    - Church, Samuel and Church, Cynthia to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1822 Apr 6 (Folder 11)
  - Deeds, 1825-1868 (Folder 12)
    - Yale, Stephen to Landon, James land in Canaan, Conn., 1827 Mar 31 (Folder 12)
    - Robbins, Samuel and Beebe, Asahel to Landon, James land in Salisbury, Conn., 1825 Nov 28 (Folder 12)
    - Landon, Henry and Yale, Anson to Landon, George land in Salisbury, Conn., 1868 May 2 (Folder 12)
  - Estate of Burrall, Jonathan, 1806 May 23 (Folder 13)
  - Estate of Landon, John, 1834 Sep 27 (Folder 14)
  - Estates, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 15)
  - License, Landon, James to be a retailer of wines and distilled spiritous liquors, 1816 Jan 2 (Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1898-1935 (Folder 17)
    A photograph; essay "Summer Sports"; reproduction bank notes; birth announcement, Dorothy Clare (1928); calling card; dance ticket (1917); permit to construct a fence (1898); "Activities of My Senior Year," Lois Bloomer (1935).
  - Miscellaneous, 1879, 1928 (Folder 18)
    "The Well Spring and Missionary Echoes" (1879) and "The Atlanta Journal" (Jan 15, 1928).
  - Receipt for taxes, 1840 Jan 26 (Folder 19)
  - Will, Ingraham, Miles, 1893 Dec 7 (Folder 20)